[
    {
        "course": "agriculture",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 1,
        "year": 1992,
        "question": "<p> Discuss briefly four factors that cause food shortages in Nigeria</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Four factors that cause food shortages in Nigeria are:</p><p>(a) Poor storage and preservation facilities: (i) Most agricultural products are perishable. (ii) Lots of farm products are lost because of lack of storage facilities. (iii) Most produce are wasted due to poor storage. (iv) Technical know-how on food storage is inadequate or lacking.</p><p>(b) Poor transportation network: (i) Presence of bad roads prevent evacuation of produce to market and this leads to wastage</p><p>(ii) The number of vehicles are inadequate. (iii) There is high cost of transportation. (iv) Most farms are not linked by roads and this eventually leads to wastage of produce.</p><p>(c) Lack of finance or credit facilities: (i) Peasant farmers have no access to credit facilities to expand their farm-land, (ii) High interest rate charged by banks prevents borrowing by farmers. (iii) Farmers do not have the required collateral security to enable them secure loan for expansion. (iv) Poor finance results in the purchase of inferior farm inputs which result in food shortage.</p><p>(d) Poor harvesting and processing techniques: (i) Premature harvesting results in food shortages. (ii) Late harvesting also results in food shortages. (iii) Bad method of harvesting also causes food shortages. (iv) Lack of modern methods of food processing also causes food shortages.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "agriculture",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 2,
        "year": 1992,
        "question": "<p>Discuss briefly eight advantages of agricultural mechanization in Nigeria</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Eight advantages of agricultural mechanisation in Nigeria include the following:</p><p>(i)Agricultural mechanization enhances timeliness of farm operations.</p><p>ii) It saves time.</p><p>(iii) Agricultural mechanization increases productivity.</p><p>(iv) It reduces health hazards.</p><p>(v) It promotes specialization of available manpower.</p><p>(vi) It encourages cooperation among farmers.</p><p>(vii) It also increases farm revenue.</p><p>(viii) It promotes agro-allied industrial establishment</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "agriculture",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 3,
        "year": 1992,
        "question": "<p>List and discuss the process of soil formation</p>",
        "answer": "<p>The process of soil formation include:</p><p>(1) PHYSICAL PROCESS: (i) The grinding of rock surfaces by solid materials carried by wind. water and moving ice results in the breaking of the rocks. (ii) The freezing and melting of ice within the rock results in the breakage of rocks (iii) The continuous expansion and contraction of rocks due to variations in the intensity of temperature results in the breaking down of rocks. (iv) The action of running water also eats up the rocks. resulting in breaking down of rocks;</p><p>(2) BIOLOGICAL PROCESS: (I) The actions of some animals like earthworm and termite cause rock to break. (ii) The burrowing activities of earthworm and termite into rocks cause their breakage. (iii) Roots of plants which penetrate rocks also help to break down the rocks. (iv) Human activities during tillage, use of plough and harrow also indirectly break down rocks.</p><p>(3) CHEMICAL PROCESS (i) Solution: Water dissolves soluble minerals or rocks in the soil. (ii) Oxidation: The reaction of oxygen with rocks results in breakage of rocks. Carbonation: Carbon dioxide which dissolves in water to form a weak carbonic acid reacts with rock to break it down. (iv) Hydration : The attachment of water to rocks results in their breakage.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "agriculture",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 4,
        "year": 1992,
        "question": "<p>(a) (i) Define the term irrigation (ii) Mention two types of irrigation (b) Discuss briefly six problems association with irrigation.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a)(i) Irrigation is the artificial application of water to soil or land in order to supplement short fall in rain. (ii) Two types of irrigation are: (i) Surface irrigation e g. flooding, furrow, contour ditch. (ii) Overhead irrigation e.g. Sprinkler and Drip</p><p>(b) Six problems associated with irrigation are:(i) Inadequate water source from streams, rivers and lakes. (ii) Irrigation equipment are expensive to purchase (iii) Pests from dry surroundings may invade and damage crops on irrigated lands. (iv) Lack of technical know-how on the operations of irrigation. (v) Vectors of diseases like snails, tse-tse fly breeds freely in irrigated areas. (vi) Disease-causing organisms increase with humidity due to irrigation.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "agriculture",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 5,
        "year": 1992,
        "question": "<p>Discuss eight economic importance of insect pests in crop production</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Eight economic importance of insect pests in crop production include the following:</p><p>(i) Insect pests reduce the quality of crops either in the field or in the store.</p><p>(ii) They destroy crops in the field through their biting chewing, sucking and burrowing activities.</p><p>(iii) They reduce the yield and may even lead to total crop failure. (iv) Farmers profits are drastically reduced.</p><p>(v) Cost of production is increased as large sum of money is expended on their control</p><p>(vi) There is also reduction in viability of stored produce.</p><p>(vii) They are disease carrying agents (or vectors).</p><p>(viii) They render vegetables and fruits unattractive and unmarketable. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "agriculture",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 6,
        "year": 1992,
        "question": "<p>Discuss the production of yam under the following headings : (a) materials of propagation; (b) soil requirement; (c) land preparation; (d) planting and spacing; (e) cultural practices (f) three major pests and their control.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Production of yam: (A) Materials of propagation : Yam seeds, yarn setts and mini-setts are used for propagation</p><p>(B) Soil requirement: Yarn requires (i) loamy soil rich in humus (ii) sandy loam soil (iii) well drained soil</p><p>(C) Land preparation This includes (i) the clearing of the land or vegetation (ii) Ploughing and harrowing (iii) Making of ridges )r mounds or heaps. (D) Planting and spacing: (i) Early planting is done at the onset of dry season (Oct - Nov) (ii) Late planting is done at the beginning of rainy season (Feb - March) (iii) Yarn seeds/setts are placed in the soil with cut surface up but slanted (iv) Spacing is 90 cm x 100 cm</p><p>(E) Cultural practices : These include: (i) The application of appropriate fertilizer. (ii) Regular weeding to ensure the growth of crop. (iii) Mulching to prevent evaporation and Insure water conservation. (iv) Staking to spread out leaves to receive sunlight (v) Training of vines.</p><p>(F) Three major pests and their control are: (i) Yam beetle Control : By dusting seed yam or yam sett with insecticides eg Aldrin dust before planting (ii) Termites Control : (i) Destroy the termitorium or ant hill (ii) Spray with insecticides (iii) cricket : Spray with insecticides</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "agriculture",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 7,
        "year": 1992,
        "question": "<p>(a) Name five breeds each of cattle and pig that can be found in Nigeria (b) State six general characteristics rabbits</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a) Five breeds of cattle that can be found in Nigeria are:</p><p>i) White Fulani</p><p>(ii) Sokoto Gudali</p><p>(iii) Muturu</p><p>(iv) Ndama .</p><p>(v) Kuri</p><p>(b) Five breeds of pig that can be found in Nigeria are:</p><p>(i) Large white</p><p>(ii) Large black</p><p>(iii) Duroc Jersey</p><p>(iv) American Land race</p><p>(v) Yorkshire</p><p>(c) Six characteristics of rabbits are:</p><p>(i) Rabbits possess a short gestation period (31 days).</p><p>(ii) They have a small body size.</p><p>(iii) They are very prolific with large litter size.</p><p>(iv) They have good quality meat which is even more palatable than chicken.</p><p>(v) They grow very fast and reach maturity weight in about 5 - 6 months.</p><p>(vi) They are efficient converter of wide range of vegetable matter. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "agriculture",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 8,
        "year": 1992,
        "question": "<p>a) Name the causative agent of each of the following livestock diseases: (i) food and mouth; (ii) rinderpest; Newcastle (b) Name three animals that can be affected by each of the diseases listed in (a). (c) State fo symptoms of foot and mouth disease and three symptoms of each for rinderpest and Newcastle diseases</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a) The causative agent of: (i) Foot and mouth disease is virus (ii) Rinderpest disease is virus (iii) Newcastle disease is virus</p><p>(b) Three animals that can be affected by each of the diseases in (a) above are: (i) Foot and Mouth disease - Cattle, Sheep and Goat. (ii) Rinderpest disease - Cattle, Pig, Sheep. (iii) Newcastle disease - Domestic fowl, Turkey, Duck.</p><p>(c) Four symptoms of foot and mouth disease are: (i) Formation of blister on the mucous membrane of the mouth (ii) Lameness (iii) Inflammation of the teats and udder (iv) Lesion in the interdigital spaces of the hoofs.</p><p>Three symptoms of Rinderpest disease are: (i) High fever (ii) Difficult breathing and loss of weight (iii) Loss of appetite and high mortality. Three symptoms of Newcastle disease are: (i) Nervous disorder or twisting of the neck (ii) Presence of greenish diarrhoea (iii) High mortality and low egg production.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "agriculture",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 9,
        "year": 1992,
        "question": "<p>Discuss eight problems which an agricultural extension worker can face in the discharge of his duties.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Eight problems which an agricultural extension worker can face in the discharge of his duties are:</p><p>(i) Language barrier leads to improper dissemination of new innovations.</p><p>(ii) Inadequacy of well trained extension workers makes him have a wider area and more farmers than he can cope with.</p><p>(iii) Inadequate resources such as finance and materials tend to hinder his performance.</p><p>(iv) High level of illiteracy among farmers may slow down the rate of adoption of new innovations.</p><p>(v) Inadequate publicity - mass media are not often fully utilised in publicising extension programmes.</p><p>(vi) Poor transportation or lack of it retards the performance of the extension worker.</p><p>(vii) Insufficient motivation of extension worker by way of remuneration makes him reluctant to work.</p><p>(viii) Unfavourable attitude of rural farmers toward government programmes, makes adoption of new innovations difficult. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "agriculture",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 10,
        "year": 1992,
        "question": "<p>List and discuss four functions of a farm manager in a farm business.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Four functions of a farm manager</p><p>(a) Organisation: The farm manager (1) secures suitable land for farming. (ii) determines what to produce. (iii) . determines s the scale of production. (iv) procures credit or loan for farming.</p><p>(b)  Administration: The farm manager (1) supervises the work on the farm. (ii) arranges work rosters. (iii) directs staff on day to day activities.(iv) Makes arrangement for staff welfare</p><p>(c) Production: The farm manager (i) is responsible for purchase and use of farm inputs. (ii) ensures the adequate supply of feeds. (iii) makes use of modern farming  techniques. (iv) ensures the health of animals/crops on the farm.</p><p>(d) Marketing: The farm manager (i) determines what to sell (ii) determines how much to sell (iii) determines when to sell to make huge profits (iv) is responsible for processing of produce.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    }
]